{"full_question": "2 Sam and two friends put letters in envelopes on Monday. The three of them take two hours to put 600 letters in envelopes. (a) On Tuesday Sam has three friends helping. Working at the same rate, how many letters should the four of them be able to put in envelopes in two hours? (a) .................................. [2] (b) Working at the same rate, how much longer would it take four people to put 1000 letters in envelopes than it would take five people? (b) .................................. [4] (c) Sam says It took two hours for three people to put 600 letters in envelopes. If I assume they work all day, then in one day three people will put 7200 letters in envelopes because 600 × 12 = 7200. Why is Sam’s assumption not reasonable? What effect has Sam’s assumption had on her answer? [2]", "full_answer": "2 (a) 800 2 1 AO1.3b 1 AO3.1c M1 for unitary work, e.g. 1 person does 200 letters in 2 hours (b) 30 minutes oe 4 2 AO2.1a 2 AO3.1d M1 for 1 person does 100 letters in 1 hour M1 for 5 people do 1000 letters in 2 hours M1 for 4 people do 1000 letters in 2.5 hours FT from their rate in (a) throughout (c) Correct comment on the reasonableness of her assumption e.g. ‘She has assumed that ‘all day’ means ‘for 24 hours’, but it is not reasonable for them to work without a break.’ Correct comment on the effect it will have on the answer e.g. ‘They can’t work at that rate for that long, so her answer is an over-estimate.’ 2 1 AO3.4a 1 AO3.5 B1 for each"}
{"full_question": "3 Abi, Ben and Carl each drop a number of identical drawing pins, and count how many land with the pin upwards. The table shows some of their results.\n1umber of pins \ndropped1umber landing \nµpin up’\nAbi 10 4\nBen 30 9\nCarl 100 35\n(a) Abi says\n As a drawing pin can only land with its pin up or with its pin down,\n the probability of a drawing pin landing ‘pin up’ is 1\n2.\n Criticise her statement.\n [1]\n(b) Carl’s results give the best estimate of the probability of a drawing pin landing µpin up’. \nExplain why.\n[1]\n(c) Two pins are dropped. \n Estimate the probability that both pins land µpin up’.\n(c) .............................. [2]", "full_answer": "3 (a) Outcomes not equally likely oe 1 1 AO3.4b \n(b) Larger number of trials 1 1 AO3.4a \n(c) 0.09 - 0.16 2 1 AO1.3a 1 AO2.1b M1 for 248150 or 0.352 or any reasonable estimate (FT their (b))"}
{"full_question": "4 John is going to make chocolate squares to sell.\n  There are just three ingredients, chocolate, peanut butter and crisped rice, mixed in the ratio  4 : 2 : 3 respectively.\n (a) How much of each ingredient will he need to make 900  g of mixture?\n(a) chocolate ................................... g\npeanut butter ............................. g\ncrisped rice ................................ g\n[2]\n (b) A bar of chocolate weighs 200  g and costs £2.50.\n  A jar of peanut butter contains 250  g and costs £1.70.\n  A packet of crisped rice contains 300  g and costs £2.00.\n  John makes 4.5  kg of mixture, from which he can cut 100 chocolate squares.\n  He charges 60p for each square and sells all 100 squares.\n  How much profit does he make?\n(b) £ ........................... [5]", "full_answer": "4 (a)  400 g 200 g 300 g\n2 \n1 AO1.3a \n1 AO3.1c  M1 for 9 soi   \n(b)  Profit = £18.20\n5 2 AO1.3b 2 AO3.1d 1 AO3.3 M1 Multiply their weights by 5 M1 Find number of each required M1* calculate total cost  *M1 dep subtract from £60"}
{"full_question": "A bag contains only red and blue marbles. Yasmine takes one marble at random from the bag. The probability that she takes a red marble is  1 3 . Yasmine returns the marble to the bag and adds five more red marbles to the bag. The probability that she takes one red marble at random is now  1 2 . How many marbles of each colour were originally in the bag? .................................. red marbles ................................. blue marbles [3]", "full_answer": "5 red 20 blue"}
{"full_question": "The lengths of the sides of two squares are integers, when measured in cm. The difference between the areas of the two squares is 36 cm2. Find the lengths of the sides of the two squares.\n.............................. cm\n.............................. cm\n[3]", "full_answer": "8 cm\n10 cm\n3 1 AO1.3a 1 AO3.1b 1 AO3.2 M1 for listing square numbers and finding differences M1 for square rooting their pair of square numbers"}
{"full_question": "8 Safety rules on a campsite require Sarah to set up her barbecue at least 4 m from her tent. She decides to measure this distance using her stride length. Sarah knows that her stride length is 0.8 m, rounded to the nearest 0.1 m. Find the minimum number of strides Sarah will need to take to guarantee that her barbecue is a safe distance from her tent.", "full_answer": "8 6 3 1 AO1.3b 1 AO3.1d 1 AO3.3 B1 for 0.75 m M1 for 4'0.75'their Or 5 x 0.75 = 3.75"}
{"full_question": "9 A sculptor needs to lift a piece of marble. It is a cuboid with dimensions 1 m by 0.5 m by 0.2 m. Marble has a density of 2.7 g/cm³. The sculptor’s lifting gear can lift a maximum load of 300 kg. Can the lifting gear be used to lift the marble? Justify your decision. [4]", "full_answer": "Volume of cuboid = 100 000 cm³ Mass of cuboid = 270 kg Yes, because 270 < 300 kg"}
{"full_question": "Show that line 3y = 4x - 14 is perpendicular to line 4y = -3x + 48. [4]", "full_answer": "Fully correct explanation, finding gradients of both lines and showing that the gradients’ product equals -1\n\nB1 for gradient of first line is 4/3 \n\nB1 for gradient of second line is -3/4\n\nM1 for finding the product of their gradients oe"}
{"full_question": "15 (a) Write this list of numbers in order, smallest first. (a) .................  ..................  .................  ................. [2] VmDOOHVt (b) Write (1 + )2 in the form D + E. (b) .................................. [3]", "full_answer": "15 (a) 22035, 2.5 , , 6.833 2 2 AO1.3b B1 if one is in the wrong place, but others are in the correct order or reverse order (b) 42 3+ 3 3 AO1.3a M1 for expanding 21 3 1 3 3 3 3     B1 for 3 ×3 = 3 soi"}
{"full_question": "Bethany says that (2 x)2 is always greater than or equal to 2 x. Decide whether she is correct or not. Show your working to justify your decision. [3]", "full_answer": "e.g. When x = 0.1 (2x)2 = 0.04 2x = 0.2 So (2x)2 < 2x which contradicts Bethany’s statement So it is not always true 3 2 AO2.4a 1 AO2.5a M1 for attempting to demonstrate that for some value of x in range 1<20< < <x it is not true A1 for complete working A1 for explanation or M1 for attempt including squaring bracket A1 for complete solution for either x < 0 or 1<2<x A1 for explanation or B1 for a counter example given without working"}
{"full_question": "17 (a) Write down the exact value of tan 60°. (a) ............................................ [1]\n\n (b) Find the exact area of this triangle. (b) ..................................... cm2 [4]", "full_answer": "17 (a) 3 1 1 AO1.1  \n\n(b) 24 3 4 4 AO1.3b M1* for height43their tan 60 A1 for 12 or 43 3 *M1 Dep for 1243 their ‘12’  "}
{"full_question": "P, Q, R and S are the midpoints of O;, ;Y, Y= and O= respectively.  = a,  = b and  = c. Show that PQ is parallel to SR.  [5]", "full_answer": "ZY = -2c + 2a + 2b\nSR=  c + (-c + a + b) so SR = a + b\nPQ =  a + b\nSR = PQ so they are parallel"}
{"full_question": "19 The prices of two phones are in the ratio x : y. When the prices are both increased by £20, the ratio becomes 5 : 2. When the prices are both reduced by £5, the ratio becomes 5 : 1. Express the ratio x : y in its lowest terms.\n............... : ............... [6]", "full_answer": "19  4 : 1\n\n- 6\n2 AO1.3b\n4 AO3.1d\nM1 for (x + 20) : (y + 20) = 5 : 2 or (x – 5) : (y – 5) = 5 : 1\nA1 for + 20 5=+ 20 2xy oe\nA1 for 55=51x–y– oe\nM1 for solving their simultaneous equations\nA1 for x = 80 or y = 20 \nDo not accept wrong notation for ratio in the final mark, e.g. for 4/1, 4, etc"}
